Finding Aid for Hilmer Gellein papers, 1925-1946 and undated
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hilmer Gellein papers 1925-1946 and undated
Gellein, Hilmer.
0.3 linear feet
851280 Aa 2
Clerk of the Detroit (Michigan) Recorders Court and director of the state department of corrections during the gubernatorial administration of Frank Murphy. Reports and other papers concerning the Michigan state penal system; and material on the Sweet Murder Trial of 1925 and the career of Frank Murphy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Hilmer Gellein (donor no. 4807 ) and came to the library beginning in 1969.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Hilmer Gellein was clerk of Detroit Recorder's Court presided over by Frank Murphy. During his time as court stenographer, Gellein was witness to perhaps the most significant case before Judge Murphy, the Ossian Sweet murder trials of 1925-26. Years later, following Murphy's election as governor of Michigan in 1936, Gellein was appointed commissioner of pardons and paroles.
The collection contains reports and other papers concerning the Michigan state penal system. There is also material collected on the Ossian Sweet Murder Trial of 1925 and the career of Frank Murphy.
Subjects:
Crime.; Michigan. Dept. of Corrections.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Sweet, Ossian, 1895-1960.
- Topical files
  - Sweet Trial, 1925 and undated (Box 1)
  - Frank Murphy, 1926-1946 (Box 1)
  - Frank Murphy Manuscript Biography, undated (Box 1)
  - State Department of Corrections
    - Speeches, 1938 and undated (Box 1)
    - Papers, undated and 1936-1939 (Box 1)
      - undated (Box 1)
      - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
      - 1938 (Box 1)
      - 1939 (Box 1)